<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<CVD_SDOH>
<TEXT><![CDATA[616. BMC Health Serv Res. 2014 Jan 8;14:10. doi: 10.1186/1472-6963-14-10.

Determinants of health after hospital discharge: rationale and design of the  Vanderbilt Inpatient Cohort Study (VICS).

Meyers AG, Salanitro A, Wallston KA, Cawthon C, Vasilevskis EE, Goggins KM,  Davis CM, Rothman RL, Castel LD, Donato KM, Schnelle JF, Bell SP, Schildcrout  JS, Osborn CY, Harrell FE, Kripalani S(1).

Author information: (1)Division of General Internal Medicine and Public Health, Department of  Medicine, Vanderbilt University, 1215 21st Ave S, Suite 6000 Medical Center  East, Nashville 37232, TN, USA. sunil.kripalani@vanderbilt.edu.

BACKGROUND: The period following hospital discharge is a vulnerable time for  patients when errors and poorly coordinated care are common. Suboptimal care  transitions for patients admitted with cardiovascular conditions can contribute  to readmission and other adverse health outcomes. Little research has examined  the role of health literacy and other social determinants of health in  predicting post-discharge outcomes. METHODS: The Vanderbilt Inpatient Cohort Study (VICS), funded by the National  Institutes of Health, is a prospective longitudinal study of 3,000 patients  hospitalized with acute coronary syndromes or acute decompensated heart failure.  Enrollment began in October 2011 and is planned through October 2015. During  hospitalization, a set of validated demographic, cognitive, psychological,  social, behavioral, and functional measures are administered, and health status  and comorbidities are assessed. Patients are interviewed by phone during the  first week after discharge to assess the quality of hospital discharge,  communication, and initial medication management. At approximately 30 and 90  days post-discharge, interviewers collect additional data on medication  adherence, social support, functional status, quality of life, and health care  utilization. Mortality will be determined with up to 3.5 years follow-up.  Statistical models will examine hypothesized relationships of health literacy  and other social determinants on medication management, functional status,  quality of life, utilization, and mortality. In this paper, we describe  recruitment, eligibility, follow-up, data collection, and analysis plans for  VICS, as well as characteristics of the accruing patient cohort. DISCUSSION: This research will enhance understanding of how health literacy and  other patient factors affect the quality of care transitions and outcomes after  hospitalization. Findings will help inform the design of interventions to  improve care transitions and post-discharge outcomes.

DOI: 10.1186/1472-6963-14-10 PMCID: PMC3893361 PMID: 24397292 [Indexed for MEDLINE]]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<Social_Connections spans="1844~1858" text="social support" id="Soc0" comment=""/>
<Education spans="962~977" text="health literacy" id="Ed0" comment=""/>
<Education spans="2050~2065" text="health literacy" id="Ed1" comment=""/>
<Healthcare_Access spans="1900~1924" text="health care  utilization" id="He0" comment=""/>
<Education spans="2419~2434" text="health literacy" id="Ed2" comment=""/>
<Healthcare_Access spans="2100~2121" text="medication management" id="He1" comment=""/>
</TAGS>
<META/>
</CVD_SDOH>