<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<CVD_SDOH_updated>
<TEXT><![CDATA[607. Prev Chronic Dis. 2014 Sep 4;11:E153. doi: 10.5888/pcd11.140044.

Determinants of major cardiovascular risk factors among participants of the  South Carolina WISEWOMAN program, 2009-2012.

Nahhas GJ(1), Daguise V(2), Ortaglia A(3), Merchant AT(3).

Author information: (1)University of South Carolina, Arnold School of Public Health, Department of  Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Discovery I Building, 915 Greene St, Room 465,  Columbia, SC 29208. E-mail: nahhas@email.sc.edu. (2)South Carolina Department of Health and Environmental Control, Columbia,  South Carolina. (3)University of South Carolina, Columbia, South Carolina.

INTRODUCTION: Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is the leading cause of death among  US women, accounting for 25% of all deaths in this population. Approximately 65%  of these deaths occur in asymptomatic women. Hypertension, hypercholesterolemia,  and diabetes mellitus (diabetes) are major risk factors for CVD and can be  treated effectively if identified at an early stage. METHODS: Data were available from 3,572 uninsured first-time female participants  aged 40 to 65 years, referred by their health professional to the South Carolina  Well-Integrated Screening and Evaluation for Women Across the Nation (SC  WISEWOMAN), 2009-2012. All women completed a structured health-risk and behavior  questionnaire. Anthropometric measures were recorded and data on clinical  risk-factors were collected. Prevalence-ratios (PRs) were obtained by predictive  multivariable log-linear modeling. RESULTS: The prevalence of risk factors was 34.7% for uncontrolled hypertension,  9.3% for hypercholesterolemia, and 21% for diabetes. Prevalence of untreated  hypertension was 15.6%; hypercholesterolemia, 8%; and diabetes, 4%. The greatest  significant predictor of hypercholesterolemia was hypertension (PR = 4.37) and  vice versa (PR = 2.39). The greatest significant predictors of diabetes were  obesity (PR = 2.23), family history of diabetes (PR = 2.02), and  hypercholesterolemia (PR = 1.85). Being obese (PR = 1.36), overweight (PR =  1.23), aged 60 years or more (PR = 1.26), and black (PR = 1.14) were significant  predictors of having at least one CVD risk factor. Being black (PR = 1.09) was  the only significant predictor of having comorbid conditions. CONCLUSION: Prevalence of uncontrolled CVD risk factors was high among  participants in the SC WISEWOMAN program. These findings confirm that the  program is reaching high-risk women who are in need of interventions to reduce  their risk for CVD through lifestyle changes.

DOI: 10.5888/pcd11.140044 PMCID: PMC4157556 PMID: 25188278 [Indexed for MEDLINE]]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<Origin spans="148~162" text="South Carolina" id="O0" comment=""/>
<Origin spans="716~718" text="US" id="O1" comment=""/>
<Gender spans="719~724" text="women" id="G0" comment=""/>
<Gender spans="836~841" text="women" id="G1" comment=""/>
<Healthcare_Access spans="1049~1058" text="uninsured" id="He0" comment=""/>
<Gender spans="1070~1076" text="female" id="G2" comment=""/>
<Age spans="1091~1110" text="aged 40 to 65 years" id="Ag0" comment=""/>
<Origin spans="1157~1171" text="South Carolina" id="O2" comment=""/>
<Gender spans="1218~1223" text="women" id="G3" comment=""/>
<Gender spans="1274~1279" text="women" id="G4" comment=""/>
<Age spans="2071~2092" text="aged 60 years or more" id="Ag1" comment=""/>
<Ethnicity_Race spans="2110~2115" text="black" id="Et0" comment=""/>
<Ethnicity_Race spans="2203~2208" text="black" id="Et1" comment=""/>
<Gender spans="2393~2400" text="program" id="G5" comment=""/>
<Gender spans="2465~2470" text="women" id="G6" comment=""/>
</TAGS>
<META/>
</CVD_SDOH_updated>