<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<CVD_SDOH>
<TEXT><![CDATA[
S: Subjective
Chief Complaint:
 “I’ve been feeling more tingling in my feet and my blood sugars have been higher than usual.”
History of Present Illness:
 Mr. John Doe is a 58-year-old male with a known history of Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus (T2DM), Hypertension, and Hyperlipidemia who presents for routine follow-up. Over the past month, he has noticed increased numbness and tingling in both feet, worse at night. The symptoms are bilateral, non-radiating, and described as “pins and needles.” He denies any new trauma, redness, or ulcers. He has also observed fasting blood glucose levels between 160-190 mg/dL and post-prandial readings occasionally exceeding 220 mg/dL, which is a change from his prior average of 130–150 mg/dL fasting. He has not changed his medication or diet significantly. He admits to some recent increased stress and skipped exercise due to workload.
He denies vision changes, shortness of breath, chest pain, orthopnea, paroxysmal nocturnal dyspnea, palpitations, dizziness, or syncope. No abdominal pain, diarrhea, or constipation. No hematuria or dysuria. No recent infections or fevers.
Medications:
Metformin 1000 mg BID


Lisinopril 20 mg daily


Atorvastatin 40 mg nightly


Aspirin 81 mg daily


Allergies:
 No known drug allergies (NKDA)
Past Medical History:
Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus, diagnosed 2014


Hypertension


Hyperlipidemia


Obesity (BMI 31.2)


Past Surgical History:
Appendectomy, 1990


No recent surgeries


Family History:
Father: T2DM, deceased from MI at age 68


Mother: Hypertension, alive, age 82


No family history of cancer


Social History:
Non-smoker


Drinks alcohol occasionally (1–2 beers/week)


Denies illicit drug use


Works full time as an accountant


Lives with wife, independent in ADLs


Review of Systems:
General: No weight change, no fever, no chills


Neurological: Reports tingling in both feet; no weakness, no falls


Cardiovascular: Denies chest pain, palpitations


Pulmonary: No shortness of breath or cough


GI: No abdominal pain, nausea, or vomiting


GU: No dysuria or hematuria


Skin: No rash or wounds noted


Musculoskeletal: No joint pain or swelling



O: Objective
Vital Signs:
BP: 138/82 mmHg


HR: 78 bpm


RR: 16/min


Temp: 98.6 °F


SpO₂: 98% on room air


Weight: 198 lbs


Height: 5’9”


BMI: 31.2 (Obese)


Physical Exam:
General: Alert and oriented, NAD


HEENT: PERRLA, EOMI, no oral lesions


Neck: No lymphadenopathy, thyroid non-enlarged


Cardiac: RRR, no murmurs, rubs, or gallops


Lungs: Clear to auscultation bilaterally


Abdomen: Soft, nontender, no organomegaly


Extremities: No edema, pulses 2+ bilaterally


Neuro:


CN II-XII grossly intact


Decreased pinprick sensation in bilateral feet up to ankles


Reflexes diminished at Achilles, normal at patella


No tremor or muscle atrophy


Skin: Intact, no ulcers, no erythema


Labs: (Most recent labs from 1 week ago)
HbA1c: 8.3% ↑ (previous: 7.1% six months ago)


Fasting glucose: 174 mg/dL


LDL: 96 mg/dL


HDL: 42 mg/dL


Triglycerides: 180 mg/dL


Creatinine: 1.0 mg/dL


eGFR: >60


Urine microalbumin: 32 mg/g



A: Assessment
Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus – Poorly controlled


HbA1c increased from 7.1% to 8.3% in 6 months


Home glucose readings elevated


Likely contributing factors: decreased physical activity, stress, possible early neuropathy


No evidence of nephropathy or retinopathy at this visit


Peripheral Neuropathy – Likely diabetic origin


Progressive bilateral tingling and decreased sensation in feet


No evidence of ulcers or active infection


Consistent with length-dependent sensory neuropathy


Hypertension – Controlled


BP today 138/82 mmHg


No reported symptoms, continues Lisinopril


Hyperlipidemia – Borderline LDL, lifestyle reinforcement needed


LDL improved with statin, but TG slightly elevated


Reinforce dietary adherence and follow-up labs in 6 months


Obesity – Stable, but no weight loss


BMI remains >30


Encourage increased physical activity and dietary adherence



P: Plan
For Diabetes:
Add GLP-1 receptor agonist (e.g., semaglutide) starting at 0.25 mg weekly to help with glycemic control and weight management


Continue Metformin 1000 mg BID


Reinforce dietary counseling: refer to dietitian for 1:1 session


Encourage return to regular physical activity (e.g., 30 mins walk daily, 5x/week)


Recheck HbA1c in 3 months


Continue home glucose monitoring; patient instructed to log values


For Neuropathy:
Start Gabapentin 100 mg TID, titrate as needed


Monitor for side effects: dizziness, somnolence


Foot care education provided: inspect daily, avoid walking barefoot, report any ulcers or cuts


Schedule diabetic foot exam every 6 months


For Hypertension and Hyperlipidemia:
Continue current regimen (Lisinopril, Atorvastatin)


No changes today


For Obesity and Lifestyle:
Reinforce importance of exercise and portion control


Provided resources for local diabetes education classes


Discussed potential role of weight loss in improving glycemic control and neuropathy symptoms


Follow-up:
3-month follow-up for repeat labs, foot exam, and diabetes reassessment


Call sooner if neuropathy symptoms worsen or new signs of infection develop


Patient Understanding & Agreement:
 The patient verbalized understanding of his new medication and lifestyle plan. He is motivated to improve his control and agrees to follow up as scheduled.


]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<Age spans="173~184" text="58-year-old" id="A0" comment=""/>
<Gender spans="185~189" text="male" id="G0" comment=""/>
<Marital_Status spans="1721~1736" text="Lives with wife" id="MS0" comment=""/>
<Alcohol_Use spans="1613~1657" text="Drinks alcohol occasionally (1–2 beers/week)" id="AU0" comment=""/>
<Tobacco_Use spans="1600~1610" text="Non-smoker" id="TU0" comment=""/>
<Illicit_Drug_Use spans="1660~1683" text="Denies illicit drug use" id="IDU0" comment=""/>
<Stress spans="822~838" text="increased stress" id="S0" comment=""/>
<Physical_Activity spans="843~859" text="skipped exercise" id="PA0" comment=""/>
<Nutrition_and_Diet spans="3820~3837" text="dietary adherence" id="NaD0" comment=""/>
<Nutrition_and_Diet spans="3970~3987" text="dietary adherence" id="NaD1" comment=""/>
<Physical_Activity spans="3938~3965" text="increased physical activity" id="PA1" comment=""/>
<Physical_Activity spans="4261~4322" text="regular physical activity (e.g., 30 mins walk daily, 5x/week)" id="PA2" comment=""/>
<Treatment_Adherence spans="4353~4419" text="Continue home glucose monitoring; patient instructed to log values" id="TA0" comment=""/>
<Employment spans="1686~1718" text="Works full time as an accountant" id="E0" comment=""/>
</TAGS>
<META/>
</CVD_SDOH>